Today, I'm going to talk about SELF-ASSESSMENTS.
Everybody knows self-assessments is really important in terms of performance management.
Basically, it's a piece of document that you officially present to your manager:
what you have done in this performance cycle.
However, a common mistake a lot of people make is:
create a NEW STORY in their self-assessment,
in the hope of your manager is going to actually DIG into the new story during the performance management cycle.
It's not the best way.
Because essentially, your manager is really trying to recall
their PERCEIVED REALITY during the whole cycle,
even before your self-assessment landed in his or her desk.
Essentially, you are trying to present information
to MATCH with the reality that is already in your manager's mind.
If you present something that is completely NEW —
THAT IS A RISK.
It's either: you've done something, but it's never in your manager's eye,
or the impact is not in your manager's view —
which is a problem.
Or you are fabricating something — which is even WORSE.
So the best way to make sure your impact is really in your manager's mind is:
during all of the ONE-ON-ONES across the whole performance management cycle —
being six months, or being a whole year —
using all the one-on-ones to present YOUR IMPACT,
to present the DATA you changed,
to present the NEEDLE you moved.
Only when you are doing those things, your manager will have
a SHARED REALITY with you of what you have actually changed.
And then your self-assessment will become a SUMMARY view
of what's already in your manager's head.
And that is the best way to making sure your self-assessment LANDED in the right way.
Hope this helps.